In December of 2010,
في ديسمبر 2010
the city of Apatzingán
مدينة اباتشينغان
in the coastal state of Michoacán, in Mexico,
في ولاية ميتشواكان الساحلية، المكسيك،
awoke to gunfire.
استيقظت على صوت اطلاق النار.
For two straight days,
ليومين متتاليين،
the city became an open battlefield
اصبحت المدينة عبارة عن ساحة معركة
between the federal forces
بين القوات الفدرالية
and a well-organized group,
و مجموعة منظمة جداً،
presumably from the local criminal organization,
من المحتمل انها من المنظمة الاجرامية المحلية،
La Familia Michoacana, or the Michoacán family.
لا فاميليا ميتشواكان، او عائلة ميتشواكانا
The citizens didn't only experience incessant gunfire
لم يختبر المواطنين اطلاق النار المتواصل فحسب
but also explosions
بل التفجيرات
and burning trucks used as barricades across the city,
و شاحنات محترقة استخدمت كحواجر في جميع أنحاء المدينة،
so truly like a battlefield.
و كأنها ساحة معركة حقيقية.
After these two days,
بعد هذين اليومين،
and during a particularly intense encounter,
و خصوصا اثناء مواجهة شديدة،
it was presumed that the leader of La Familia Michoacana,
أشيع ان قائد لا فاميليا ميتشوكانا،
Nazario Moreno, was killed.
نازاريو مورينو، قد قتل.
In response to this terrifying violence,
و كرد لهذا العنف المرعب،
the mayor of Apatzingán
قرر عمدة اباتشينغان
decided to call the citizens to a march for peace.
ان يدعو المواطنين لمسيرة سلام.
The idea was to ask for a softer approach
كانت الفكرة ان نطلب نهجا اكثر ليونة
to criminal activity in the state.
للنشاط الاجرامي في الولاية.
And so, the day of the scheduled procession,
وهكذا، في اليوم الموعود للمسيرة،
thousands of people showed up.
أتي العديد من الناس.
As the mayor was preparing to deliver
و بينما كان العمدة يجهز لالقاء
the speech starting the march,
خطاب البدء في المسيرة،
his team noticed
لاحظ فريقه
that, while half of the participants
انه في حين نصف المشاركين
were appropriately dressed in white,
كانوا يرتدون الأبيض
and bearing banners asking for peace,
و يحملون الرايات يطلبون السلام،
the other half was actually marching
كان النصف الاخر يسيرون
in support of the criminal organization
لدعم المنظمة الاجرامية
and its now-presumed-defunct leader.
ومن يفترض انه زعيمها السابق
Shocked, the mayor decided to step aside
صدمة، المحافظ قرر أن يتنحى جانباً
rather than participate or lead a procession
على أن يتصرف أو يقود المسيرة
that was ostensibly in support of organized crime.
والتي كانت ظاهرياً لدعم الجرائم المنظمة
And so his team stepped aside.
وفريقه أيضاً تنحى جانباً
The two marches joined together,
المسيرتان أنضمت لبعضهما
and they continued their path
وربطوا طريقهم
towards the state capital.
بإتجاه عاصمة الولاية
This story of horrific violence
هذه القصة المرعبة والعنيفة
followed by a fumbled approach
تمت متابعتها بوصول متخبط
by federal and local authorities as they tried
بواسطة الفيدراليين والسلطات المحلية كلما كانوا يحاولون
to engage civil society,
التداخل في المجتمع المدني
who has been very well engaged by a criminal organization,
والذي كان مرتبط ببعضه جداً بواسطة المنظمات الإجرامية
is a perfect metaphor for what's happening in Mexico today,
هو استعارة كاملة لما يحدث اليوم في المكسيك
where we see that our current understanding
أينما نرى أن فهمنا الحالي
of drug violence and what leads to it
لعنف المخدرات وما تقود إليه
is probably at the very least incomplete.
هو ربما الأقل نقصانا
If you decided to spend 30 minutes trying
إذا قررت قضاء 30 دقيقة تحاول
to figure out what's going on with drug violence in Mexico
أن تكتشف ماذا يجري في عنف المخدرات في المكسيك
by, say, just researching online,
أو عن طريق البحث على الانترنت
the first thing you would find out is that
أول شيء ستكتشفه هو
while the laws state that all Mexican citizens are equal,
بينما القانون في الولاية يقول ان كل المواطنين المكسيكيين هم سواسية
there are some that are more
البعض هناك أكثر قليلاً
and there are some that are much less equal than others,
وهناك أقل في التساوي من الآخرين
because you will quickly find out
لأنك ستجد وبسرعة
that in the past six years
أن الستة سنوات الماضية
anywhere between 60 and 100,000 people
أي مكان بين 60 و 100.000 شخص
have lost their lives in drug-related violence.
فقدوا حياتهم في العنف المرتبط بالمخدرات
To put these numbers in perspective,
لوضع هذه الأرقام في منظور
this is eight times larger than the number of casualties
هذا أكبر بثمانية مرات من رقم الخسائر
in the Iraq and Afghanistan wars combined.
في حروب العراق وأفغانستان مجتمعة
It's also shockingly close to the number of people
وهي أيضاً بشكل صادم قريبة من رقم الأشخاص
who have died in the Syrian civil war,
الذين ماتوا في الحرب الأهلية في سوريا
which is an active civil war.
التي هي حرب نشطة.
This is happening just south of the border.
هذا يحدث جنوب الحدود
Now as you're reading, however,
الان، وكما تقرأ، بطريقة ما
you will be maybe surprised that you will quickly
ستكون ربما متفاجئ بأنك وبسرعة
become numb to the numbers of deaths,
ستصبح مخدراً بسبب أرقام القتلى
because you will see that these are sort of abstract numbers
بسبب أنك سترى أن هذه هي نوعاً ما أرقام نظرية
of faceless, nameless dead people.
لمجهولين، اشخاص قتلى مجهولي الهوية
Implicitly or explicitly, there is a narrative
ضمناً أو علنا، هذه القصة
that all the people who are dying
بأن كل الأشخاص الذين يموتون
were somehow involved in the drug trade,
كانوا بشكل ما متورطين في تجارة المخدرات
and we infer this because they were either tortured
ونحن نستنتج هذا بسبب أنهم إما تم تعذيبهم
or executed in a professional manner,
أو أعدامهم بأسلوب محترف
or, most likely, both.
أو، على الأرجح، كلاهما
And so clearly they were criminals
واضح جداً أنهم كانوا مجرمين
because of the way they died.
بسبب الطريقة التي ماتوا فيها
And so the narrative is that somehow these people
لذلك القصة هي بشكل ما هؤلاء الأشخاص
got what they were deserved.
حصلوا على ما كانوا يستحقون
They were part of the bad guys.
كانوا جزءاً من الأشخاص السيئين
And that creates some form of comfort
وهذا ينشئ بعضاً من الاريحية
for a lot of people.
للكثير من الناس
However, while it's easier to think
على أية حال، طالما أنه من السهل ان تفكر
of us, the citizens, the police, the army,
فينا، في المدنيين، في الشرطة، في الجيش.
as the good guys, and them, the narcos,
كأشخاص جيدين، وهم، ضباط مكافحة المخدرات
the carteles, as the bad guys,
العملاء السريين، كأشخاص سيئين
if you think about it,
إذا فكرت فيها
the latter are only providing a service to the former.
الخطاب يقدم فقط خدمة للمذكور أولاً
Whether we like it or not,
سواء أعجبنا ذلك أم لا
the U.S. is the largest market
الولايات المتحدة هي أكبر سوق
for illegal substances in the world,
للمواد الغير قانونية في العالم
accounting for more than half of global demand.
معتبر لأكثر من نصف الطلب في العالم
It shares thousands of miles of border with Mexico
إنها تشارك آلاف الأميال من المحدود مع المكسيك
that is its only route of access from the South,
هذا هو طريقها الوحيد للدخول من الجنوب
and so, as the former dictator of Mexico, Porfirio Diaz,
ولذلك، كرئيس أسبق للمكسيك، بورفيريو دياز
used to say, "Poor Mexico,
كان يقول" المكسيك المسكينة،
so far from God and so close to the United States."
بعيدة عن الله وقريبة من الولايات المتحدة"
The U.N. estimates that there are 55 million users
الأمم المتحدة قدرت أن هناك 55 مليون مستخدم
of illegal drugs in the United States.
للمخدرات الغير قانونية في الولايات المتحدة
Using very, very conservative assumptions,
بإستخدام توقعات محافظة جداً جداً
this yields a yearly drug market on the retail side
هذا الإنتاج السنوي لسوق المخدرات في جانب التجزئة
of anywhere between 30 and 150 billion dollars.
من أي مكان بين 30 و 150 مليار دولار
If we assume that the narcos only have access
إذا افترضنا أن ضباط المكافحة لديهم صلاحية الدخول
to the wholesale part, which we know is false,
إلى جزء الجملة، والذي نعرف أنه غير صحيح،
that still leaves you with yearly revenues
هذا يتركك مع الأرباح السنوية
of anywhere between 15 billion and 60 billion dollars.
لأي مكان بين 15 مليار و 60 مليار دولار.
To put these numbers in perspective,
لوضع هذه الأرقام على الواقع
Microsoft has yearly revenues of 60 billion dollars.
مايكروسوفت لديها إيرادات سنوية من 60 مليار دولار
And it so happens that this is a product that,
وهذا يحدث أن هذا المنتج الذي
because of its nature, a business model
بسبب طبيعته، نموذج تجاري
to address this market requires you
لعنونة هذا السوق يتطلب منك
to guarantee to your producers
أن تضمن منتجك
that their product will be reliably placed
بأن منتجاتهم ستكون بكل ثقة مكانهم
in the markets where it is consumed.
في الأسواق مكان استهلاكها.
And the only way to do this, because it's illegal,
والطريقة الوحيدة لعمل ذلك، بسبب أنها غير قانونية،
is to have absolute control of the geographic corridors
هو انك تملك التحكم الكامل بكل الممرات الجغرافية
that are used to transport drugs.
والتي تستخدم لنقل المخدرات
Hence the violence.
ومن ثم العنف.
If you look at a map of cartel influence and violence,
إذا نظرت إلى خريطة إتفاقيات التأثير والعنف
you will see that it almost perfectly aligns
سترى أن معظمها متحيزة بشكل كامل
with the most efficient routes of transportation
في أغلب الطرق تأثيراً في النقل
from the south to the north.
من الجنوب للشمال
The only thing that the cartels are doing
الشيء الوحيد الذي تفعله الإتفاقية
is that they're trying to protect their business.
هو أنهم يحاولون حماية أعمالهم
It's not only a multi-billion dollar market,
انه ليس مليارات متعددة من الدولارات في السوق
but it's also a complex one.
لكنه أيضاً معقدة
For example, the coca plant is a fragile plant
مثال: نبتة الكوكايين هي نبتة ضعيفة
that can only grow in certain latitudes,
والتي تنبت في بيئة محددة
and so it means that a business model
وهذا يعني أن نموذج الأعمال
to address this market requires you to have
لعنونة هذا السوق تتطلق أن تملك
decentralized, international production,
لامركزية، انتاج دولي
that by the way needs to have good quality control,
هذا بالمناسبة تحتاج إلى أن تملك تحكم بالجودة الممتازة
because people need a good high
لأن الناس يحتاجون إلى مخدر جيد
that is not going to kill them
والذي لا يقتلهم
and that is going to be delivered to them when they need it.
وهو سيتم توصيله لهم عندما يحتاجونه
And so that means they need to secure
وهذا يعني أنهم يحتاجون إلى تأمين
production and quality control in the south,
التحكم بالإنتاج والجودة في الجنوب
and you need to ensure that you have
وتحتاج للتأكد بانك تملك
efficient and effective distribution channels
كفائة وفعالية قنوات التوزيع
in the markets where these drugs are consumed.
في الأسواق حيثما تستهلك المخدرات
I urge you, but only a little bit,
أنا أحثك، قليلاً فقط،
because I don't want to get you in trouble,
لأني لا أريدك أن تقع في المشاكل
to just ask around and see how difficult it would be
لتسأل في الأرجاء ولترى كم هي صعبة
to get whatever drug you want, wherever you want it,
لتحصل على ما تحتاج من المخدرات، أينما تحتاجه
whenever you want it, anywhere in the U.S.,
وقتما تحتاجه، أي مكان في الولايات المتحدة.
and some of you may be surprised to know
بعضكم يتفاجئ إذا عرف
that there are many dealers that offer a service
أن هناك الكثير من المروجين الذين يعرضون خدمة
where if you send them a text message,
بإرسالهم رسالة نصية
they guarantee delivery of the drug
يضمنون لك توصيل للمخدر
in 30 minutes or less.
في 30 دقيقة أو أقل
Think about this for a second.
فكر فيها لثانية
Think about the complexity
فكر في تعقيد
of the distribution network that I just described.
شبكة التوزيع التي وصفتها.
It's very difficult to reconcile this
إنه من الصعب أن تنسجم
with the image of faceless, ignorant goons
مع هذه الصورة لمجهولين، حمقى وجاهلين
that are just shooting each other,
الذين فقط يقتلون بعضهم البعض
very difficult to reconcile.
صعب جداً أن تنسجم
Now, as a business professor, and as any business professor would tell you,
كبروفيسور في ادارة الأعمال، ومثل أي بروفيسور للادارة سيقول لك
an effective organization requires
التنظيم الفعّال يتطلب
an integrated strategy that includes
استراتيجية متكاملة تتضمن
a good organizational structure, good incentives,
كيان تنظيمي جيد، محفزات جيدة
a solid identity and good brand management.
هوية راسخة وإدارة جيدة للعلامة تجارية
This leads me to the second thing that you would learn
هذا يقودني للشيء الثاني الذي ستتعلمونه
in your 30-minute exploration of drug violence in Mexico.
في النصف ساعة من اكتشفاكم لعنف المخدرات في المكسيك.
Because you would quickly realize,
لأنكم ستلاحظون بسرعة
and maybe be confused by the fact,
وستشوشون بالحقيقة
that there are three organizations
هناك ثلاث منظمات
that are constantly named in the articles.
والتي تسمى دائماً في المقالات
You will hear about Los Zetas,
ستسمع عن لوس زيتاس
the Knights Templar, which is the new brand
نايتس تامبلر، وهي ماركة جديدة
for the Familia Michoacana that I spoke about at the beginning,
لفاميليا ميشواغانا والتي تحدثت عنها في البداية
and the Sinaloa Federation.
و اتحاد السينالوا
You will read that Los Zetas is this assortment
ستقرأ أن لوس زيتاس هو مجموعة
of sociopaths that terrify the cities that they enter
من المنبوذين في المجتمع الذين يرعبون المدن التي يدخلونها
and they silence the press,
ويسكتون الصحف
and this is somewhat true, or mostly true.
وهذا نوعاً ما صحيح، أو معظمه صحيح
But this is the result of a very careful branding
لكن هذا هو ناتج ماركة حذرة جداً
and business strategy.
واستراتيجية عمل
You see, Los Zetas is not just
كما ترى، لوس زيتاس ليست فقط
this random assortment of individuals,
هذه المجموعة العشوائية من الأفراد
but was actually created by another criminal organization, the Gulf Cartel,
لكنها في الحقيقة أنشئت بواسطة منظمة إجرامية أخرى، خليج كارتيل
that used to control the eastern corridor of Mexico.
والتي كانت تتحكم بالممر الشرقي من المكسيك
When that corridor became contested, they decided
عندما أصبح هذا الممر متنازع عليه، قرروا
that they wanted to recruit
أنهم يريدون تجنيد
a professional enforcement arm.
يد تعزيزية محترفة لهم.
So they recruited Los Zetas:
لذلك جندوا لوس زيتاس:
an entire unit of elite paratroopers
وحدة كاملة من نخبة المظليين
from the Mexican Army.
من الجيش المكسيكي.
They were incredibly effective as enforcers for the Gulf Cartel,
كانوا مؤثرين بشكل مذهل كتعزيز لخليج كارتيل
so much so that at some point, they decided
لدرجة أنه في نقطة ما، قرروا
to just take over the operations,
أن يتبنوا العمليات
which is why I ask you to never keep tigers as pets,
وهو ما نصحتكم به أن لا تأخذوا النمور كحيوانات أليفة
because they grow up.
لأنهم سيكبرون
Because the Zetas organization was founded in treason,
بسبب ان منظمة الزيتاس أوجدت عن طريقة خيانة
they lost some of the linkages to the production and distribution
خسروا بعض الروابط للإنتاج والتوزيع
in the most profitable markets like cocaine,
في أغلب الأسواق المربحة مثل الكوكايين
but what they did have,
لكن ماحصلوا عليه
and this is again based on their military origin,
وهذا مرة أخرى معتمد على أصولهم العسكرية
was a perfectly structured chain of command
هو سلسلة منظمة متكاملة من القيادة
with a very clear hierarchy
مع سلم رتب واضح جداً
and a very clear promotion path that allowed them
وخط ترقية واضح جداً يسمح لهم
to supervise and operate across many, many markets
بالإشراف والعمل عبر الكثير والكثير من الأسواق
very effectively,
بشكل مؤثر جداً
which is the essence of what a chain of command seeks to do.
والذي كان الجوهر في ما كانت تسعى سلسلة القيادة لفعله
And so because they didn't have access
وبسبب أنهم لم يكن بإمكانهم الدخول
to the more profitable drug markets,
إلى أسواق المخدرات الأكثر ربحية
this pushed them and gave them the opportunity
هذا دفعهم وأعطاهم فرصة
to diversify into other forms of crime.
للتنوع لأشكال إجرامية أخرى
That includes kidnapping, prostitution,
وهذا يشمل، الإختطاف، الدعارة
local drug dealing and human trafficking,
الترويج المحلي للمخدرات والإتجار بالبشر
including of migrants that go from the south to the U.S.
ويشمل ذلك المهاجرين الذين يذهبون من الجنوب إلى الولايات المتحدة
So what they currently run is truly
ما يشغلونه حالياً هو بصدق
and quite literally a franchise business.
وحرفياً عمل بإمتياز
They focus most of their recruiting on the army,
يركزون أكثر مجنديهم على الجيش
and they very openly advertise for better salaries,
وهم يعلنون علناً عن رواتب أفضل
better benefits, better promotion paths,
مزايا أفضل، سير ترقيات أفضل
not to mention much better food,
بدون ذكر أفضل نوع من الطعام
than what the army can deliver.
أفضل ما يمكن أن يقدمه الجيش
The way they operate is that
الطريقة التي يعملون بها هي
when they arrive in a locality,
عندما يصلون إلى موقع
they let people know that they are there,
يخبرون الناس انهم في هذا المكان
and they go to the most powerful local gang
ويذهبون إلى أقوى العصابات المحلية
and they say, "I offer you
ويقولون "أنا أعرض عليك
to be the local representative of the Zeta brand."
أن تكون ممثل محلي لماركة زيتا"
If they agree -- and you don't want to know
إذا وافقوا- لا تريدون أن تعرفوا
what happens if they don't --
ماذا سيحدث إذا لم يوافقوا-
they train them and they supervise them
يدربوهم ويشرفون عليهم
on how to run the most efficient criminal operation
في كيف تدير العمليات الإجرامية الأكثر كفاءة
for that town, in exchange for royalties.
لهذه البلدة مقابل إعطائهم صفات النبل
This kind of business model obviously depends
هذا النوع من نماذج الأعمال يعتمد بشكل واضح
entirely on having a very effective brand of fear,
كاملاً على الحصول على فعالية ماركة الخوف
and so Los Zetas
ولوس زيتاس
carefully stage acts of violence
تنظم بحرص أعمال العنف
that are spectacular in nature,
التي هي في طبيعتها
especially when they arrive first in a city,
خاصة إذا وصلوا أولاً إلى مدينة
but again, that's just a brand strategy.
لكن مرة أخرى، هذه فقط استراتيجية العلامة التجارية
I'm not saying they're not violent,
انا لا أقول أنهم غير عنيفين
but what I am saying is that even though you will read
لكن ما اقوله هو حتى ولو أنك ستقرأ
that they are the most violent of all,
أنهم الأكثر عنفاً بين الجميع
when you count, when you do the body count,
عندما تحصي، عندما تحصي عدد القتلى
they're actually all the same.
هم في الواقع كلهم يتشابهون
In contrast to them, the Knights Templar
مقارنة بهم، ذا نايتس تيمبلر
that arose in Michoacán
والتي نشأت في ميتشواكان
emerged in reaction to the incursion
برزت في ردة فعل للغارة
of the Zetas into the state of Michoacán.
من الزيتاس على ولاية ميتشواكان
Michoacán is a geographically strategic state
ميتشواكان ولاية استراتيجية جغرافياً
because it has one of the largest ports in Mexico,
بسبب أن لديها واحدة من أكبر المنافذ في المكسيك
and it has very direct routes to the center of Mexico,
ولديها طريق مباشر جداً لوسط المكسيك
which then gives you direct access to the U.S.
والذي يعطيك دخول مباشر إلى الولايات المتحدة
The Knights Templar realized very quickly
ذا نايتس تمبلر لاحظوا بشكل سريع جداً
that they couldn't face the Zetas on violence alone,
أنهم لا يستطيعون مجابهة الزيتاس بالعنف لوحدهم
and so they developed a strategy
لذلك طوروا استراتيجية
as a social enterprise.
كمؤسسة اجتماعية.
They brand themselves as representative of
روجوا لأنفسهم على أنهم ممثلين
and protecting of the citizens of Michoacán
وحامين للمدنيين في ميتشواكان
against organized crime.
ضد الجرائم المنظمة
Their brand of social enterprise means
ترويجهم لهذه المغامرة الاجتماعية تعني
that they require a lot of civic engagement,
أنهم يحتاجون إلى الكثير من التدخل المدني
so they invest heavily in providing local services,
لذلك استثمروا بشكل قوي في تقديم خدمات محلية
like dealing with home violence,
مثل التعامل مع العنف المنزلي،
going after petty criminals, treating addicts,
ملاحقة توافه الجرائم، علاج المدمنين
and keeping drugs out of the local markets
والحفاظ على عدم وصول المخدرات إلى الأسواق المحلية
where they are,
الأماكن الموجودين فيها
and, of course, protecting people
وبالطبع، يحمون الناس
from other criminal organizations.
من المنظمات الاجرامية الأخرى
Now, they kill a lot of people too,
الآن، يقتلون الكثير من الناس أيضاً
but when they kill them,
لكن عندما يقتلونهم
they provide very careful narratives and descriptions
يقدمون بحرص شديد قصص وتوصيفات
for why they did them,
لتبيين أسباب قتلهم
through newspaper insertions, YouTube videos,
خلال إدراجها في الصحف، او مقطع على اليوتيوب
and billboards that explain that the people who were killed
أو لوحات توضح ان الناس الذين قتلوا
were killed because they represented a threat
قتلوا بسبب انهم يمثلون خطر
not to us, as an organization, of course,
ليس لنا، كمنظمة بالطبع
but to you, as citizens.
بل لكم، كمدنيين
And so we're actually here to protect you.
لذلك نحن في الحقيقة هنا حتى نحميكم
They, as social enterprises do,
هم ، كما تفعل المؤسسات الاجتماعية
have created a moral and ethical code
أنشئوا قانون أخلاقي ومعنوي
that they advertise around,
الذي أعلنوا عنه
and they have very strict recruiting practices.
ولديهم تدريب جنود قاسي
And here you have the types of explanations
هنا لدينا أنواع التوضيحات
that they provide for some of their actions.
التي يقدمونها لبعض تصرفاتهم
They have actually retained access
لديهم في الحقيقة دخول متحفظ
to the profitable drug trade,
لربح تجارة المخدرات
but the way they do it is, because they control all of Michoacán,
لكن الطريقة التي ينفذونها بها ، لأنهم يتحكمون بكل ميتشواكان
and they control the Port of Lázaro Cárdenas,
ويتحكمون في منفذ لازارو كارديناس
they leverage that to, for example,
هم يضغطون عليه بسبب، مثل
trade copper from Michoacán that is legally created
تجارة النحاس من ميتشواكان والذي قانونياً تم انشاءه
and legally extracted
وقانونياً تم استخراجه
with illegal ephedrine from China
مع الايفيدرين الغير قانوني من الصين
which is a critical precursor for methamphetamines
والذي هو نذير شؤم على الميثامفيتامين
that they produce, and then they have partnerships
الذي يقدمونه، وبعد ذلك حصلوا على شراكة
with larger organizations like the Sinaloa Federation
مع تنظيم أكبر مثل اتحاد سينالوا
that place their products in the U.S.
والذي يضع انتاجهم في الولايات المتحدة
Finally, the Sinaloa Federation.
أخيراً، اتحاد سينالوا
When you read about them, you will often read about them
عندما تقرأ عنهم، ستقرأ غالباً عنهم
with an undertone of reverence and admiration,
مع إعجاب وتقدير خفي
because they are the most integrated
بسبب أنهم الأكثر تكاملاً
and the largest of all the Mexican organizations,
والأكبر من كل المنظمات المكسيكية
and, many people argue, the world.
و-كما يعتقد الكثير من الناس - في العالم أيضاً
They started as just sort of a transport organization
بدأوا كنوع ما كمنظمة نقل
that specialized in smuggling between the U.S.
والمتخصصة في تهريب الممنوعات بين الولايات المتحدة
and the Mexican borders,
والمكسيك على الحدود
but now they have grown
لكن الأن قد كبروا
into a truly integrated multinational
بشكل متكامل ومتعدد الجنسيات حقاً
that has partnerships in production in the south
والتي كان لها شركات في الإنتاج من الجنوب
and partnerships in global distribution
وشراكات في التوزيع العالمي
across the planet.
في جميع أنحاء المعمورة
They have cultivated a brand of professionalism,
لديهم علامة تجارية مصقولة بالإحتراف
business acumen and innovation.
فطنة عمل وإبتكار
They have designed new drug products
لقد صمموا منتج مخدر جديد
and new drug processes.
وعمليات جديدة للمخدرات.
They have designed narco-tunnels
صمموا انفاق مخدرات
that go across the border,
التي تمر عبر الحدود
and you can see that these are not
وبإمكانكم أن ترون أنه هذه ليست
"The Shawshank Redemption" types.
كأنواع الفيلم السينمائي (ذا شاوشنك ريدمبشن)
They have invented narco-submarines and boats
ابتكروا غواصات حربية وقوارب للمخدرات
that are not detected by radar.
التي لن تكتشف بالرادار
They have invented drones to transport drugs,
ابتكروا طائرات بدون طيار لنقل المخدرات
catapults, you name it.
مقاليع، أو سمها ما شئت.
One of the leaders of the Sinaloa Federation
واحد من القادة في اتحاد سينالوا
actually made it to the Forbes list.
في الواقع نجح في الوصول إلى قائمة فوربس
[#701 Joaquin Guzman Loera]
رقم 701: خواكين غوزمان لويرا
Like any multinational would, they have specialized
مثل عمل أي متعدد جنسيات، قد تخصصوا
and focused only in the most profitable part of the business,
وركزوا فقط على الجزء الأكثر ربحاً من العمل
which is high-margin drugs like cocaine,
والذي هو المخدرات المدخلة للأرباح مثل الكوكايين
heroine, methamphetamines.
الهيروين، الميثامفيتامين.
Like any traditional Latin American multinational would,
مثل أي عادة لاتيني أمريكي متعدد جنسية في العمل
the way they control their operations
الطريقة التي يتحكمون بها في عملياتهم
is through family ties.
هي خلال العلاقات العائلية
When they're entering a new market, they send
عندما يدخلون إلى سوق جديدة، يرسلون
a family member to supervise it,
عضو من العائلة للأشراف عليه
or, if they're partnering with a new organization,
أو، إذا أصبحوا شركاء مع منظمة جديدة
they create a family tie,
ينشئون علاقات عائلية
either through marriages or other types of ties.
إما عن طريق الزواجات او عن طريق أنواع أخرى من الارتباطات
Like any other multinational would,
مثل ما يعمله أي متعدد جنسيات آخر
they protect their brand by outsourcing
هم يحمون الماركة الخاصة بهم عن طريق مصدر خارجي
the more questionable parts of the business model,
الجزء الأكثر إثارة للتساؤل في نموذج العمل
like for example, when they have to engage
كمثال ، عندما يضطرون للدخول
in violence against other criminal organizations,
في عنف ضد منظمة إجرامية أخرى
they recruit gangs and other smaller players
يجندون عصابات وأطراف صغيرة أخرى
to do the dirty work for them,
ليعملون لهم عملهم القذر
and they try to separate their operations
ويحاولون أن يفصلوا عملياتهم
and their violence and be very discrete about this.
وعنفهم وتكون منفصلة جداً عن بعضها.
To further strengthen their brand,
ليتقدمون بشكل أقوى لعلامتهم التجارية
they actually have professional P.R. firms
هم في الحقيقة يملكون شركات علاقات عامة محترفة
that shape how the press talks about them.
والتي تشكل رؤية الصحافة عنهم
They have professional videographers on staff.
ويملكون مصورين محترفين في فريقهم
They have incredibly productive ties
يملكون علاقات تحميهم بشكل مذهل
with the security organizations
مع منظمات أمنية
on both sides of the border.
على جانبي الحدود
And so, differences aside,
لندع الاختلافات جانباً
what these three organizations share
الذي تشاركه هذه المنظمات الثلاثة
is on the one hand, a very clear understanding
من جانب، تفاهم واضح جداً
that institutions cannot be imposed from the top,
بحيث أن المؤسسات لا يمكن أن الضغط عليها من الأعلى
but rather they are built from the bottom up
لكن بدلاً من ذلك يبنون من القاعدة للرأس
one interaction at a time.
و يقومون بتفاعل واحد في كل مرة.
They have created extremely coherent structures
قد أنشئوا كيان منطقي جداً
that they use to show the inconsistencies
الذي يستخدمونه ليظهروا التناقضات
in government policies.
في سياسات الحكومة
And so what I want you to remember from this talk
والذي أريدكم ان تتذكروه من هذه المحاضرة
are three things.
ثلاثة أشياء
The first one is that drug violence
الأولى هو أن عنف المخدرات
is actually the result
هو في الحقيقة نتيجة
of a huge market demand
من طلب سوق ضخم
and an institutional setup that forces
والضبط المؤسساتي الذي أرغم
the servicing of this market to necessitate violence
خدمات هذا السوق تستلزم العنف
to guarantee delivery routes.
لضمان طرق التوصيل
The second thing I want you to remember
الشيء الثاني، أريدكم أن تتذكروا
is that these are sophisticated,
أن هذه العمليات معقدة جداً
coherent organizations
والمنظمات متماسكة
that are business organizations,
و هي منظمات أعمال
and analyzing them and treating them as such
وتحليلها و معاملتها
is probably a much more useful approach.
هي ربما أكثر المقاربات المفيدة .
The third thing I want you to remember
الشيء الثالث الذي اريدكم أن تتذكروه
is that even though we're more comfortable
حتى ولو أننا مرتاحين أكثر
with this idea of "them,"
مع فكرة (هم)
a set of bad guys separated from us,
مجموعة من الأشخاص السيئين المنفصلين عنا
we are actually accomplices to them,
نحن في الحقيقة متواطئين معهم
either through our direct consumption
إما عبر إستهلاكنا المباشر
or through our acceptance of the inconsistency
أو بالرغم من أن قبولنا بالإلزام
between our policies of prohibition
بين سياساتنا بالحظر
and our actual behavior of tolerance
وتصرفنا الفعلي بالتسامح
or even encouragement of consumption.
أو حتى التشجيع على الإستهلاك
These organizations service, recruit from,
هذه الخدمات من المنظمات، تجند منا
and operate within our communities,
وتعمل ضمن مجتمعاتنا،
so necessarily, they are much more integrated
بالضرورة، هم متكاملين جداً
within them than we are comfortable acknowledging.
داخلها أكثر مما نعترف بأريحية
And so to me the question is not whether
بالنسبة لي، السؤال هو ليس ما إذا
these dynamics will continue the way they have.
كانت هذه الديناميكية ستستمر بالطريقة التي كانت عليه
We see that the nature of this phenomenon
نرى أن طبيعة هذه الظاهره
guarantees that they will.
تضمن لها بالاستمرار
The question is whether we are willing to continue
السؤال هو ما اذا كنا سنستمر
our support of a failed strategy
بدعم استراتيجيات فاشلة
based on our stubborn, blissful, voluntary ignorance
المعتمدة على العناد، الهناء، الجهل الطوعي
at the cost of the deaths of thousands of our young.
لتكفلة موت الضحايا من الالاف من شبابنا
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)